---
layout: null
permalink: /feed/
---
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
	<title>GISforThought</title>
	<description>GIS blog focussed on Open Source GIS.</description>
	<link>http://gisforthought.com</link>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2021 09:15:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <sy:updatePeriod> hourly </sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency> 1 </sy:updateFrequency>
    <generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>
<item>
<title>
30 Day Map Challenge 2021
</title>
<link>http://gisforthought.com/2021/11/30/30-day-map-challenge-2021.html</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
30 Day Map Challenge 2021
</description>
<content:encoded>
<p>This November I once again took part in the 30 Day Map Challenge started by <a href="https://twitter.com/tjukanov">Topi Tjukanov</a>.</p> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/announcement.PNG" alt="Categories" /></p> <p>I had done it the first year (<a href="https://gisforthought.com/30-day-map-challenge-2019/">30 Day Map Challenge 2019</a>), and had made a few maps for 2020 as well.</p> <p>This year I wasn’t really sure I would take part, as I had no plans and nothing prepared. But it is a great challenge. It challenges your creativity, problem solving, and map making skills. It also sets a time limit so you don’t have to worry about being perfect. And making maps is good fun.</p> <p>There were a few datasets that I had come across that I thought would be good subjects, and I got a lot of mileage out of them.</p> <h2 id="dublin-neighbourhoods">Dublin neighbourhoods</h2> <p>These included the Dublin Inquirer neighbourhood survey.</p> <p><a href="https://www.dublininquirer.com/2021/11/03/will-you-draw-your-dublin-neighbourhood-for-us">Will You Draw Your Dublin Neighbourhood for Us?</a></p> <p><a href="https://neighbourhoods.dublininquirer.com/">neighbourhoods.dublininquirer.com</a></p> <p>I think this is a great initiative, and hopefully they get a real large set of responses. They are at over 2000 already so a great start.</p> <p>I did something similar for Glasgow (<a href="https://gisforthought.com/glasgow-regions-mapped-progress-update-1/">here</a>) but only got 367 responses in total. So the power of having a well read paper behind the initiative is great. They are also reaching out to areas that have not had many responses, which is really great work.</p> <h2 id="openstreetmap">OpenStreetMap</h2> <p>I also wanted to do some maps around OpenStreetMap in Ireland. The community here has had a large push to map all of the buildings in Ireland, which has progressed well.</p> <p>But it is very much a work in progress.</p> <p><a href="https://files.osmfoundation.org/s/BD6HeiJiXTGkDMM">OSM Ireland Buildings poster from State Of The Map 2021</a></p> <h2 id="selected-maps">Selected Maps</h2> <h3 id="hexagons">Hexagons:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day4Hexagons.png" alt="Hex" /></p> <p>First of the Dublin boundaries series.</p> <p>Final interactive version: <a href="https://maps.gisforthought.com/dublin_hoods/">Here</a></p> <h3 id="openstreetmap-1">OpenStreetMap:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day5OpenStreetMap.png" alt="OpenStreetMap" /></p> <p>For OSM day I wanted to try and make the data a bit easier to use for #QGIS novices.</p> <p>I created styles that can be applied to the GEOFABRIK Shapefile extracts, <a href="https://www.geofabrik.de/data/download.html">from here</a>.</p> <p>The styles are available: <a href="https://github.com/HeikkiVesanto/QGIS_OSM_Styles">https://github.com/HeikkiVesanto/QGIS_OSM_Styles</a></p> <h3 id="red">Red:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day6Red.png" alt="Red" /></p> <p>Mac vs Mc.</p> <p>Supermac’s is an Irish fast food restaurant chain, who have had a few trademark disputes over the years with McDonald’s over the use of Mc and Mac in burger names.</p> <h3 id="3d">3D:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day11_3D.png" alt="3D" /></p> <p>This turned out a lot better than I expected.</p> <p>Was pure QGIS. Create grid (5km x 5km), zonal statistics on CORINE (Majority) and DEM (Median). New field for height rounded up to the nearest 40:</p> <p>to_int(ceil((“_h_median” / 40))) * 40</p> <p>Set colors. Create centroids with same colors. These become the Lego nubs.</p> <p>Rendered in QGIS2threejs plugin. The grid is extruded, with a height of height * 50. The centroids are cylinder rendered height * 50 + 30 * 50, so they come a bit higher, radius of 1800.</p> <p>The “rayshader” export makes it look realistic.</p> <p>Interactive: <a href="https://maps.gisforthought.com/LegoIreland/">https://maps.gisforthought.com/LegoIreland/</a></p> <p>Might be better to not use landuse, but elevation for the colours.</p> <h3 id="no-computer">No Computer:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day15_NoComp.jpg" alt="No Computer" /></p> <p>Nice to get away from the computer. Definitely promotes some creativity. But I just took it as an opportunity to walk on the beach.</p> <h3 id="land">Land:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day17_Land.png" alt="Land" /></p> <p>My favourite of my maps.</p> <p>Land use vineyard across Europe from CORINE 2020, with the major regions labelled.</p> <h3 id="ghsl">GHSL:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day23_GHSL.gif" alt="GHSL" /></p> <p>Seasonal population of the Balearic Islands.</p> <p>Data clipping in QGIS/GDAL, rendered in Aerialod, with labels with GIMP afterwards.</p> <p>This was my second favourite of my maps. I think the topic is interesting and the execution is pretty good. Was however quite manual and probably needed more exaggeration to see the differences.</p> <h3 id="historical">Historical:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day24_historical.gif" alt="Historical" /></p> <p>A time lapse of 1,831,044 buildings in Ireland being added to OpenStreetMap.</p> <p>If you want to get involved see: <a href="https://tasks.openstreetmap.ie/about">OpenStreetMap Ireland Buildings</a></p> <h3 id="globe">Globe:</h3> <p><img src="/assets/30-day-map-challenge-2021/Day28_globe.gif" alt="Globe" /></p> <p>Simple spinning globe in QGIS, but I was happy that I was able to automate the export: <a href="https://gist.github.com/HeikkiVesanto/252b7d65ba839de8a6f83065c7f27505">Gist</a></p>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
Blog Migration
</title>
<link>
https://gisforthought.com/2021/11/29/blog-migration.html
</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
Blog Migration
</description>
<content:encoded>
<h1 id="github-pages">Github Pages</h1> <p>My old hosting provider had a data breach so they shut down completely:</p> <p><a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/21/02/09/1933204/no-support-linux-hosting-shuts-down-after-cyberattack">‘No Support Linux Hosting’ Shuts Down After Cyberattack</a></p> <p>But that wasn’t really a surprise, as I was only paying $1 per month.</p> <p>Luckily I had all my posts archived in regular e-mails from WordPress, and using a combination of Flickr, Archive.org, and the original posts I think I have recovered all of the images as well.</p> <p>So we are now on Github pages.</p> <p>I ended up creating a few parsers to replace the images and links on the page:</p> <p><a href="https://github.com/HeikkiVesanto/HeikkiVesanto.github.io/blob/main/docs/python_parsers/image_parser.py">image_parser.py</a></p> <p><a href="https://github.com/HeikkiVesanto/HeikkiVesanto.github.io/blob/main/docs/python_parsers/link_parser.py">link_parser.py</a></p> <p>If you notice any issues drop me a line of Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/HeikkiVesanto">HeikkiVesanto</a></p> <p>Thanks.</p>
</content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>